<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Gerald Jackson</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2017-01-02T10:03:25-05:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Good Man Speaking Well and Mastery as Masculine Epistemologies]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/academic/rhetoric-and-masculinity/" />
  <id>/academic/rhetoric-and-masculinity</id>
  <published>2016-10-29T10:00:14-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-10-29T10:00:14-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;There is a theoretical tension between two approaches to my work, and those approaches recognize rhetoric as an art practiced by a rhetorical subject, but also recognize the inherent incompleteness of that subject as it is enmeshed in interrelationships with others. In part, this is a question of agency, but I have often sought, in my own thinking, to rectify the collapse of agency and a notion of correctness within different forms of expression. That&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/academic/rhetoric-and-masculinity/&quot;&gt;The Good Man Speaking Well and Mastery as Masculine Epistemologies&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on October 29, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Feminine Machines and Emotional Appliances]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/academic/humans-halberstam/" />
  <id>/academic/humans-halberstam</id>
  <published>2016-07-20T10:00:14-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-07-20T10:00:14-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve been watching the British Television Show [&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Humans&lt;/font&gt;](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humans_(TV_series) for a few episodes now (&lt;strong&gt;Note: I’ve finished series 1 since beginning this post&lt;/strong&gt;), and what was, and is, immediately striking about the show is how gendered practices play out across human/machine relationships. In a few cases, there are interactions that, to me, portray an interesting breakdown between the artificial and the real as material-discursive phenomena. Before I continue, I think as a side note I would say that there are many other places in which the show reifies these binaries, especially the notion of a buried consciousness inside the minds of “awakened,” sentient cyborgs, is represented by some piece or pieces of code. I think that there are more complex debates regarding the actual reality of AI to be had, but I’m not doing that here. It is in other places that I believe we get an interesting view of how gender and artificiality are used, and abused, for particular reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For those not familiar to the show, there are some light spoilers here.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The show, for those still with me, revolves around an near- or alternate-future where artificial beings, called “synthetics” or “synths,” exist as household appliances for humanity. Fashioned to mimic humanity,  these machines do not have “true” or strong AI, as a John Searle might demand, but instead function as high-level expert systems that work as servants or drones. They, physically, are indistinguishable from humans until they speak or move. While the main narrative of the show follows a group of these synths (and a human cyborg, but that is a topic for another talk) who have achieved true consciousness–they feel and express emotions, understand human subtlety and complexity (often, the non-sentience synths express robotic confusion when their human counterparts tell jokes or express sarcasm), there are a few sub-plots. One, interesting for me, is the gendered dynamics between humans and synths. Since the synths are outwardly human-like, there are a few instances (and it is implied that this is normal) where characters form emotional/sexual attachments to their synths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everyone has a synth(they are a luxury for many, like a sports car), so a split forms to broadly define two character types: those who are content to relegate synths as a normal part of the background of everyday life (that is, normalizing them as appliances), and those who constantly feel unease, unsettled by the uncanny and disconcerting relationship to human-resembling non-humans, which immediately situates many of the characters in the overlap between treating the synths as citizens, family, or friends, or appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/odi.jpg&quot; style=&quot; width: 200px; height: auto; float: left; margin: 3px;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Synths, as appliances, perform a significant amount of emotional work, work that is not predicated on any notion that a given synth is self-aware or not. Odi, an older model of synth owned by Dr. George Millican (who helped design the first synths before the events of the show), serves as a link between Dr. Millican and his deceased wife. Odi, as a computer, has memory of the painful past and often, unbidden, speaks of those events to George. George, accordingly, resists the pressure to “recycle” Odi by his health insurance provider who wishes to upgrade Odi to a newer caretaker model. Odi, unlike a picture or voice recording, is like a child that never ages. More painful for George, Odi is like a child that will say the wrong things at the wrong time, evoking the past unexpectedly–often by simply walking in the room. And yet in the articulation of his memory Odi continually links George to his past. While the insurance company sees Odi as a replaceable object, George situates Odi as an emotional appliance, a walking performance of memory that he only partially controls. This lack of total control, the lack of total control over the medium of memory, makes those memories all the more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/anita.jpg&quot; style=&quot; width: 200px; height: auto; float: right; margin: 3px;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
The notion of an emotional appliance becomes all the more relevant in this show when factoring in gender. Anita, a synth who had formerly possessed sentience but lost it after reprogramming, is purchased by Joe Hawkins, despite the protests of his wife, Laura. Anita was built as young, attractive, and gentle, a model to function in service roles such as housekeeping or care giving. Upon purchasing Anita, Joe is given her instruction manual, which includes a code to unlock “adult” mode–a mode that allows the machine to express and perform sexuality with her primary user. This becomes relevant to the relationship between Joe and Laura, as it is implied early on that Laura is distant, often leaving for work, working long hours, or finding excuses to remain out of the house. While her distance is tied to a tragedy in her past, Joe reads her distance as evidence of infidelity, and one night he activates Anita’s adult mode to satiate his own anger and frustration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once his indiscretions are brought to the attention of his family, he is shunned not only by his wife but by his children, who have come to see Anita as a member of the household. Joe, as he defends himself for his actions, repeatedly asserts that she is just a doll–she cannot feel anything, therefore nothing truly harmful was done. This denial of her as a sexual object at the moment that he is shamed by his family for objectifying her as a sexual object situates her femininity at a crossroads between her sexual appropriation, her familial appropriation, and her ability to perform the norms of gendered labor within the house. At the same time, it highlights the implications of a gendered technology: plugged in to a set of sexual, cultural, and social practices, Anita &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; already sexual because while she is compliant, she is, like Odi, not entirely under the control of the user. Her body is an appliance for Joe in multiple ways, but it also resists the total objectification that would equate her with, say, a toaster or a refrigerator. Thus her controlled agency, her programmed freedom, constructs a gender of unresisting existence–she is not a doll, and yet she is a doll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jack Halberstam, in “Automating Gender,” argues that gendered technology, rather than robbing women of some essential, naturalized essence, highlights the technicity of the gendered body. He writes that “the intelligent and female cyborg thinks gender, processes power, and converts a binary system of logic into a more intricate network” (454). That is, the melding of gender and technology into constituent parts (merging the natural and the technological), the female cyborg unsettles the distinction of technology from gender and evokes “something unsettling, something that profoundly disturbs and frightens certain authors” (454). On the one hand, this opens space for the technicity of gender, a breaking from the “natural” binary of man and women, the head and the body, technology and nature. On the other, since the female cyborg disrupts the gendered separation of nature (or the body, in this case) and technology, it disrupts social relationships of gendered power by implicating technology (as knowledge) within the collapse of that split. It refuses to mobilize gender in a natural context, and simultaneously opens the horizon of gender expression and exposes the mechanisms by which gender as technology oppresses. Joe’s usage of Anita as an emotional appliance is an example of how gendered technology exposes the violence of binary logics of sexuality. She is, in every sense of the word, helpless before Joe. I should note here that Joe is not portrayed as a violent or corrupted man. Rather, he is a confused and frustrated husband and father who, when given the opportunity, expresses that frustration on an artificially-willing female body through unquestionable sexual submission. Her automated gender is as such that she can immediately blur the lines of nature and technology in ways that reify destructive gender logics (she can have sex with Joe, but can never resist him once activated). This allows Joe a dominant sexual outlet, rather than a productive one that would question his own gendered approaches to his relationship with his wife (conversation, emotional openness, therapy, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Anita, the technological body (the bodies that are already technical) find new conduits to express gender disparity, and to circulate that disparity through the characters of the show (show can have sex with her without her resistance, but not without the resistance of the family). Emotional appliances therefore are the uncomfortable expressions of emotion that play across technology that has been seen up to now as ungendered, or at least outside of nature or the natural. Halberstam writes that “the body may be scientifically altered in order to force ‘correct’ gender identification, but desire remains as interference running across a binary technologic” (444). That is, as an emotional appliance, Anita (among others) embodies how desire is a performative aspect of technology, particularly in how technology situates bodies as usable, disposable, and sexual.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/academic/humans-halberstam/&quot;&gt;Feminine Machines and Emotional Appliances&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on July 20, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ideology and Software]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/academic/software-idology-chun/" />
  <id>/academic/software-idology-chun</id>
  <published>2016-07-20T10:00:14-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-07-20T10:00:14-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;blockquote&gt;

	&quot;In our so-called postideological society, software sustains and depoliticizes notions of ideology and ideology critique. People may deny ideology, but they don&#39;t deny software--and they attribute to software, metaphorically, greater powers than have been attributed to ideology . . . The notion of softwarehas crept into our critical vocabulary in mostly uninterrogate ways.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;Wendy Hui Kyong Chun, “On Software, or the Persistance of Visual Knowledge”.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This strikes me as especially relevant when I struggle with how Feminism and Gender Studies, as theoretical concepts and as a fields of study, have been left to the realm of representational politics in discussions of digital media. Increasingly, the mobilization of discursive studies of code have seemingly situated these studies as optional lenses outside of, or emergent phenomena from, more fundemental, gender-neutral technology. I believe this is a mistake, as we can trace the gendered scientific-militaristic origins of programming to see how practices in engineering are incredibly gendered, and still continue to propogate in software development.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/academic/software-idology-chun/&quot;&gt;Ideology and Software&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on July 20, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaching First Year Composition in an Era of Circulating Media]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/pedagogy/black-lives-matter/" />
  <id>/pedagogy/black-lives-matter</id>
  <published>2016-07-14T01:26:52-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-07-14T01:26:52-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Not too long ago, two African American men were shot by the police, re-opening some still-healing wounds for the country. One of my students, prior to class, laughed a bit ruefully and commented, “Why does it seem that so many things happen between classes?” Her comment marked a sad (and frustrated) orientation in our conversations in which our capacity to address certain events as a class was being outpaced by the sheer volume of reports of death, murder, and exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, part of this could reflect on me and what I chose to bring up. Thinking about students as critical beings has, in a way, always compelled me to think of the classroom as a place to bring up issues in our contemporary culture. This is not to rile them up or to construct a classroom of like-minded critics, but rather to ask them, first and foremost, to acknowledge that there are events in the world that escape our immediate attention, whether through our own lack of care or lack of exposure. However, as is the case in this situation, the overwhelming representation of violence, authority, and poverty in the United States is overt and, in some ways, not very complicated. I took for granted, for example, that my students remembered events like the shooting of Michael Brown in Ferguson, MO, or the choking death of Eric Garner in New York, or the Dylan Booth terrorist attack in Charleston, or the demonstrations and riots that followed many of these incidents. But overall, the specter of racial violence and the role of authority in America was sort of ephemeral, shocking, unreal in a way. And, more so, I think it was seen as tragic and unavoidable. One student opined that when it comes to movements like black lives matter, she wishes people would just be quiet because “hashtags are useless and people will forget in a week anyway.” The sadness and frustration that has no outlet, no recourse, seemingly no way out, comes to the surface and, in many ways, either burns in shocked outrage or simply dissolves into resignation (or, often, one leads in to the other).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t had much issue raising these topics, despite some anecdotes I’ve heard of teachers having different experiences. I find that, through experience over the years, I’m going to get less from it if I continue to lean on what I traditionally do in the class, and find it increasingly difficult to distinguish what I teach in the class (rhetoric, argument, writing) and what is going on in the world. Teaching “skills” or techniques increasingly provides little connection, little structure, for students to invest in, and more and more I find it a tactic of institutionalized discourse. To teach a writing class as a space to learn techniques, form, or to read the sanctioned corpus of a humanities education seems antiquated and out of touch. I look to projects like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blacklivesmattersyllabus.com/frankleonrobertsr/&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;the BLM Syllabus&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and see what pedagogy and practice are to some: a political act. I hope to, in the next weeks, research and potentially produce similar projects, to help both structure my future teaching and to offer resources and support to others doing the same.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pedagogy/black-lives-matter/&quot;&gt;Teaching First Year Composition in an Era of Circulating Media&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on July 14, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Geek Sublime]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/digital/culture/geek-sublime/" />
  <id>/digital/culture/geek-sublime</id>
  <published>2016-06-23T12:46:59-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-06-23T12:46:59-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;The New York Times recently posted a story on the operationalization of gender and race in computer code, an observation that most people will find either painfully obvious or incredibly enlightening. The former group, however, I have found do not appreciate the value of articulating such an insight to a general audience. This is disheartening, as it suggests a separation between academic specialists and the audience that they would supposedly engage (outside themselves). That is why I appreciate Vikram Chandra’s &lt;em&gt;Geek Sublime&lt;/em&gt;. Chandra, writing about the cultural aspects of computation and computer culture traces his own history with computers with incredible care and wit, inviting and educating audiences unfamiliar with either. It is clear from the very beginning that Chandra loves working on computers. A student of literature and language, Chandra began his education studying writing and literature, first pursuing the “classics” (the western, European canon) and eventually moving through the literature and history of his own Indian culture. Alongside this, his increasing interest in working on technology and helping others with their technical problems (those with some technological know-how will be familiar with this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chandra’s personal journey mirrors a cultural journey, the journey of his country post-WWII as communication and computation became heavy markets for global capital and military advancement. India, as Chandra points out, was at the forefront in importing technological know-how into local universities (ironically, by exporting students to universities in the United States and Europe). India invested money into the digital boom before there was such a boom, and as such Chandra ties together the relationship of freedom, modernization, and the global economy. Chandra’s orientation between the western and Indian culture, between literature and technology, articulates a world in which these areas are not completely separate. This is a world where algorithmic thinking is at the heart of Indian language, where the beauty of language works through code, and where critical approaches to both, each informed by the other, is necessary. Chandra’s early chapters delve into the pressing questions of race, class, and gender as technological issues, describing a culture dominated by white, western interests and practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the more technical side, his discussion of the programming language &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.muppetlabs.com/~breadbox/bf/&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Brainfuck&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and Object-Oriented Programming (OOP) begins an interesting discussion of programming as expressive, but also as interminable and exhausting. The politics of programming labor include the question of what it means to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; a laborer, to keep up in a race of conferences, new languages, and constant demands to produce and engage. This, in some ways, reminds me of other labor models in which workers are seen as white-collar, privileged, and therefore above exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I thoroughly enjoyed this book.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital/culture/geek-sublime/&quot;&gt;Geek Sublime&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on June 23, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing My Dissertation in Latex]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/software/latex-dissertation/" />
  <id>/software/latex-dissertation</id>
  <published>2016-06-23T12:46:59-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-06-23T12:46:59-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I  &lt;a href=&quot;https://latexforhumans.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;came across this site during some of my research&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/a&gt; regarding the question of how to manage a large document such as a book or dissertation outside of the Microsoft Word software. I don’t think that this is a “new” thing for some, but I don’t know  anyone using anything other than a word processor to write their dissertations (or, perhaps, Scrivener) outside of engineering or some of the sciences, which has made it hard to ask around about it. At the same time, everyone with an opinion online has warned against using Word or Word-like software (LibreOffice, Pages) to manage a large document like a dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be a big mistake, as I have to learn a few things more about the language, but as I move forward I think that I might have stumbled upon something great. The ease of creating smaller sections in separate documents that I can place within a logical structure and compile makes this method much more flexible and intuitive for me, and allows me to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;easily compile a large document after adding sections,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;control the formatting of the entire document through a central, master compilation file,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;create smaller compilation files for smaller sections (chapters in particular, which will be nice when I need to provide writing samples, and&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;manage my bibliography through software like &lt;a href=&quot;https://mendeley.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Mendeley&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which can output a bibliography as a Latex-ready database.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will probably make updates here with references that may help others as I continue.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/software/latex-dissertation/&quot;&gt;Writing My Dissertation in Latex&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on June 23, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflection at RSA 2016, Day 3]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/professional/rsa-reflections-3/" />
  <id>/professional/rsa-reflections-3</id>
  <published>2016-06-07T01:26:52-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-06-07T01:26:52-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Since I presented on the third day of the conference, I approached it in a state of exhaustion and excitement. Presenting is always exciting, but after a full day the previous day (including the Coalition of Women Scholars in the History of Rhetoric and Composition and &lt;em&gt;Enculturation&lt;/em&gt; parties) left me a bit slow to go that morning. Since our panel – 015, “Sex, Consent, and Digital Disidentifications in Queer Media and Technology” – didn’t begin until 11:00am I had time to sleep a little and prepare. I realized that I missed some interesting panels but I am never one to forego nervous, last-minute quadruple-checking of all that I needed to do, followed by multiple radings of the presentation. Luckily, my co-panelists were Jacqueline Rhodes, Jonathan Alexander, and Michael J. Faris, who were all wonderful. Much of my excitement stemmed from the fact that this was the first panel I had put together, and that my co-panelists had agreed to be a part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jacquie and Jonathan both presented on Object Oriented Ontology and the question of consent. After beginning with a discussion of OOO through Ian Bogost’s work in &lt;em&gt;Alien Phenomenology&lt;/em&gt;, Rhodes and Alexander suggested that such an approach qould not be able to give us a position to ask the question “Do Objects concent” to our use of them, and instead invoked Jane Bennet’s &lt;em&gt;Vibrant Matter&lt;/em&gt;. The claim of these speakers (who presented in tandem, alternating speaking roles in their presentation) was not an argument that objects could consent to our use, but that we can’t argue that &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; can’t consent either. To impose the question of consent on matter implies an inability to think about the inner workings of matter, but at the same time a limitation to our knowledges about the participatory nature of matter in our lives, including in how we make decisisions about concent. Their argument suggested that in considering matter as part of embodied, decision-making processes, we could in fact open up what it means to give or recieve consent for any action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael’s presentation focused on the embodied materiality of the online dating service Grindr, targeted primarily to a gay male users looking for companionship, sex, coffee, or simply conversation. True to the title of the panel, this was a “sensory ethnography,” in that Michael took us through the world of Grindr through his own experiences, displaying his user account profile and discussing when, why, and how the app participated in his life. His take on Grindr was that his connection to the app, and the communing, is such that there are powerful affective, embodied responses that the app provokes. This can come from more straightforward cues (the use of profile pictures and body shots) and on cues tied to the app itself (updates, notifications, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I prepare to go onto the market in the fall and finish my dissertation, this year’s RSA was a welcome reminder of how excited I can feel about the field and my potential place in it. It makes me much more hopeful and energized for the upcoming fall.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/professional/rsa-reflections-3/&quot;&gt;Reflection at RSA 2016, Day 3&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on June 07, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflection at RSA 2016, Day 2]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/professional/rsa-reflections-2/" />
  <id>/professional/rsa-reflections-2</id>
  <published>2016-06-02T03:36:52-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-06-02T03:36:52-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;The second day of RSA was a full one. I don’t often panel from morning to night, but with the fall Job Market coming up I wanted to be present at as many panels as possible and meet a few people. I could, throughout the 2-3 days that I was present in Atlanta, palpably feel the upcoming job search: some of these folks, hopefully, would run searches for their respective universities, perhaps sit on hiring committees, perhaps even become future colleagues. As I prepare my dissertation and my documents, I feel a mix of excitement and uncertainty, but also hope–the conversations I had tended to ground me in my work and the people who share my interests in the field, and helped calm some of the uncertainties that I felt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Panels&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most fun panels I went to on Saturday was one that I almost skipped, due to its 8:00am time. Laura Gurak and Trent Kays, in “Materiality and Digital Spaces as Agents of Rhetorics of Change” (F12) both presented on ethos in digital spaces. Dr. Gurak discussed trust and ethos in online spaces, and Kays spoke on crowdsourcing and scientific ethos. Since one of the chapters of my dissertation invokes trust in terms of computer code and network protocols, I found Dr. Gurak’s discussion of how trust and ethos constitute one another in online spaces to be fascinating. Furthermore, she discussed a hard-to-get book my Niklas Luhmann, &lt;em&gt;Trust and Power&lt;/em&gt;, which I need to get my hands on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the afternoon, I attended panel J14, “Literacy as a Rhetorical Object,” primarily to see Annette Vee discuss coding and literacy. I agreed with her general position that framing coding as literacy is perhaps justified, but also a move of power in that it creates a crisis of literacy framed around a new tool that is often harnessed for capital gains. Coding as literacy uses the rhetoric of empowerment to then create an impetus for success: those who do not gain this literacy are therefore not empowered, even though many can and should do just fine without ever learning how to code. Lynn Lewis, in her follow-up on technology and time, gave a fantastic discussion of how Pearson publishing frames education as a crisis of time and expediency, and that their technologies (Pearson Writer, Blackboard) are situated as solutions to these crises. It reminds me how firmly certain technologies are embedded within our pedagogues, even if a teacher does not necessarily incorporate tech into their classes. My USC students are all plugged in to Blackboard and, understandably, like when I use the platform as it works with all of their other classes. The local community college, Midlands Technical College, uses Brightspace D2L, and I am actually required to use the platform for grading, course content, and attendance. Lewis’ argument, however, reminded me that our technology, even if we think it in the background or an institutional nuisance, is loaded with ideological baggage and influential politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Lynn Lewis: &amp;quot;Pearson has been described as a corporate octopus&amp;quot; ... Lynn Lewis FTW &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/j14?src=hash&quot;&gt;#j14&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RSA16?src=hash&quot;&gt;#RSA16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gerald Jackson (@geraldsjackson) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/geraldsjackson/status/736631211913805824&quot;&gt;May 28, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Lynn, citing Trimbur/Marcuse: Pearson caps on literacy crisis b/c crises are typically invoked by cultural stakeholders &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/j14?src=hash&quot;&gt;#j14&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RSA16?src=hash&quot;&gt;#RSA16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gerald Jackson (@geraldsjackson) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/geraldsjackson/status/736632506292830208&quot;&gt;May 28, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Lynn: Tech is seen as neutral application for addressing seeming decaying cultural competence via literacy &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/j14?src=hash&quot;&gt;#j14&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RSA16?src=hash&quot;&gt;#RSA16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gerald Jackson (@geraldsjackson) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/geraldsjackson/status/736632718201638912&quot;&gt;May 28, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I would remiss if I didn’t mention my final panel of the day, “Rhetoric as Change, Rhetoric as Circulation” (K17). This was a speedier panel featuring authors from the upcoming book on Rhetoric and Circulation (in which I also have a chapter). Authors discussed circulation in terms of digital monuments, public graffiti, open source digital humanities projects, and others. The discussions were shorter in length due to a larger panel of participants, but the showing was great and I think it really provoked interest in the book.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/professional/rsa-reflections-2/&quot;&gt;Reflection at RSA 2016, Day 2&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on June 02, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflection at RSA 2016, Day 1]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/professional/rsa-reflections-1/" />
  <id>/professional/rsa-reflections-1</id>
  <published>2016-05-28T07:06:52-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-28T07:06:52-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;My first day at the Rhetoric Society of America Biennial Conference 2016 was actually only a half-day, unfortunately. Driving in from Columbia, SC, I spent a good portion of the day in the car passing through Georgia and South Carolina. Perhaps unrelated to the conference itself but not to my own experience, the travel west from SC to Georgia is actually incredibly nice. The road conditions also improve tremendously, but this seems to be the case no matter what direction you leave the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Presentations of Note:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joan Faber McAlister presented “Inside Amy Schumer: Celebrating and Critiquing Comedic Modes in (PostFeminism)” (D14), a great talk on Schumer, her focus on women’s issues, and the status of her popular show on Comedy Central. Faber noted that Schumer, perhaps unlike other female comedians, has reached across gendered audiences to attract an audience of men as well as women. Faber cites critics who referenced her comedy as sort of “bro,” in that it (and her stand up, if you have ever heard it) are frank in their discussion of race, class, gender, and sexuality. Schumer often takes on the character of a cluelessly spoiled white American, which situates her comedy as a biting critique of social norms thorugh parody. However, as Faber pointed out, this causes some friction in how her comedy is recieved, in that Schumer rarely addresses race overtly and her performances can reify uncomortable racial categories rather than critique them. Faber’s ultimate point, that a feminist comedic approach to cultural critique well be messy and sometimes incomplete, does not foreclose seeing Schumer’s work as important. Instead, it invites us to interrogate humor as a challenge to the cliched “humorless feminist” and investigate feminism’s role in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the “Rhetorics and Aesthetics” panel (E3), I listened to two great talks (which is great, as I attended the panel on a whim). In the first, Jess Boykin discussed comics and invitational rhetoric in “Filling the Gaps: Invitational Rhetoric and the Graphical Biography,” she uses the graphical biographies of Martin Luther King Jr., Malcom X, and Nelson Mandela to show how whitespace between panels in the comics invite readers to construct their own meaning alongside the comic. Rather than an enthymematic logic of persuasion, the whitespace invites readers into a conversation regarding the action in the comic and what it expresses. The second, “Beautiful Subversions: (re)Covering and (re)Examining the Transvestite Visualities and Feminists Rhetorics of 19th Century Author and Actor Adah Issacs Menken,”  by Jeanne Bohannon, uses archival material of Menken to show how the gendered work of drag in media found root in the theatrics and reproducibility in photography. Menken posed both in clothing that was traditionally male and female, and often blurred the lines between the two (for example, wearing men’s clothing but exposing her breasts). Bohannon argued that recovering this kind of visual rhetoric is important, in that Menken used a transvestite visuality to express her interpretations of her own gender and sexuality at a time when such images were often portrayed as lewd or corrupt. Bohannon’s work tied together a study of the medium and the archive to discuss why the rhetoric’s of Menken could be recovered as a feminist or queer rhetoric of visual media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think both panels set me up for a good conference outing. There were a few I missed early on due to my drive, but I was rewarded with some interesting discussion and ideas. I enjoyed that both of these panels, at least in some way, were dealing with media, or at least different discourses than I am used to discussing: namely sketch comedy and photography. I had done some work on African-American activists and performance through photography for a course (with a paper I hope to return to someday) so Bohannon’s talk was a great surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/professional/rsa-reflections-1/&quot;&gt;Reflection at RSA 2016, Day 1&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on May 28, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nathan Stormer, Articulation, and Order as Rhetorical Practice]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/research/stormers-articulation/" />
  <id>/research/stormers-articulation</id>
  <published>2016-05-08T10:28:19-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-08T10:28:19-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;img/women_articulate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Until we engage that question and the ideological commitment to (particular) divisions of nature and culture, all attempts to borrow from theories that critique humanism (in the name of making humanistic rhetoric more open to different ways of thinking) will assimilate and domesticate epistemological challenges (258).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: right;&quot;&gt;&quot;Articulation: A Working Paper on Rhetoric and Taxis&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stormer argues that critique of humanist theory is mired within a distinct separation of culture and nature, or more specifically discourse and materiality, which limits how we as cholars can approach new modes of rhetorical investigation. His agenda here is historiographical, in that he seeks to address rhetoric as a performative agency, rather than the product of a necessary human agency. Rhetoric, in this sense, is a product of discursive and material practices (which can be “a space, and image, a canonized activity, or a network of relationships”) rather than an innate human capacity (259). He draws from the Greek &lt;em&gt;taxis&lt;/em&gt;, the skill of mapping one’s mind into language through the ordering of discursive elements to produce a desired effect in an audience. Stormer uses this to discuss &lt;em&gt;articulation&lt;/em&gt; as a relational term: a point of articulation is the point that joins multiple  possibilities or entities, that delimits “a range of motions or possible actions” and that “defines parameters for enactment” (264). Order, &lt;em&gt;taxis&lt;/em&gt;, is refigured here not as the production of order by a human agency, but the agential capacity of order itself to express possibilities for different rhetorics. “Rhetorics” here is plural precisely because, with different material-discursive configurations, we see the production of different rhetorics from different arrangements or orders. Articulation, as the rhetorical work of order, is the production of discourse, languages, bodies, and space. Stormer argues that the study of order, “the historical rules whereby something separates from act and becomes text” is the study of articulation as an “posthumanistic historiographical perspective” (276). Where does the “text” that we analyze become a text separate from the production of rhetorical possibility that begat it? How does order, as a foundation for rhetoric, function rhetorically? What does this implicate when we think about bodies and discourses as performative?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;As defined here, articulation places agency in networks; it makes rhetoric a historically contingent phenomenon (275).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My understanding, then, is that order is not a given within a system: there is no inevitability with order. Instead, order is performative, but the nature of that performativity is rooted in the order itself as a recursive process of networks (re)iterating their structure through performing bodies and discourses. The application of such a realization, I think, has pretty wide-reaching implications for the study of performativity (and Stormer touches on gender performativity here) and the performativity of technology. In a world of technology rooted in structure and code, articulation offers us new ways to think about how digital media in particular functions rhetorically to reiterate values and practices that may not, on their surface, be recognized as such. In the above image, the word “articulate” is an adjective, denoting the (obviously gendered) notion of what it means to “be” articulate: to make sense in an orderly fashion. But a switch to the verb “articulate” shifts the understanding of the word not as a quality (good at communicating, good and recognizing order and leveraging it) but as a production of order through performance. The latter suggests the performativity Stormer describes, as it would locate within a network of practices the very question of what it means to &lt;em&gt;be articulate&lt;/em&gt;. Further, it offers a chance to think about &lt;em&gt;how to articulate&lt;/em&gt;, not as a human speaker but as a performative rhetorical structure–which, as a goal of Stormer’s, de-centers human agency as the focal point of rhetorical theory and history. Therefore, questions of gender performativity &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; media, or structural race &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; media, does not require recourse to a speaking subject for validity. Instead, practices can be traced through media structures.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/research/stormers-articulation/&quot;&gt;Nathan Stormer, Articulation, and Order as Rhetorical Practice&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on May 08, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Liquid Feedback and Coding Democracy]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/software/first-post/" />
  <id>/software/first-post</id>
  <published>2016-04-29T13:30:59-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-04-29T13:30:59-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;David Budde &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opendemocracy.net/david-budde/all-politics-swarm-intelligence-and-subterranean-politics-in-germany&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;discusses how the concept of swarm intelligence is reframing Eurpoean politics&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, using the Pirate Party as an exmaple of such political work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the Pirate Party uses a platform called “Liquid Feedback” (aka, &lt;a href=&quot;http://liquidfeedback.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;The Democracy Software&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) to perform a new politics. Budde writes that “The Pirate Party does not stand for certain policies, but for a new way of doing politics that challenges established notions of parliamentary democracy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we equate a swarm intelligence, framed as a political performance, with democracy? It seems to be radically distributed, in that the party does not vote on any particular issue, but on the issues voted on by users of their Liquid Feedback platorm. But, otherwise, while this is seemingly a move towards radical participation, it also demonstrates a concern in how we produce a democratic practice in software. Is that possible? What does it mean to “code” a democracy?&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/software/first-post/&quot;&gt;Liquid Feedback and Coding Democracy&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on April 29, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Composition Map]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/research/comp-mamap/" />
  <id>/research/comp-mamap</id>
  <published>2013-05-08T12:11:44-04:00</published>
  <updated>2013-05-08T12:11:44-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Gerald Jackson</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>geraldsjackson@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/composition.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/composition.jpeg&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So above I’m posting a PDF image of a thought map I created to aid my study for Qualifying Exams this October. It essentially marks some of the major movements of composition, starting with the teaching of speech and composition in English through some contemporary post-process theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This map is skeletal, obviously, in that I cannot hope to cover the entirety of comp theory in one document (or by myself). however, this is a start, I think, and any suggestions as to the expansion of the map, or the filling of holes in the map, or additional sources for the map, are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/research/comp-mamap/&quot;&gt;Composition Map&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Gerald Jackson at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gerald Jackson&lt;/a&gt; on May 08, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
